#### **CURRICULUM VITAE**

#### TIMOTHY WAFULA MAKOKHA,

#### Advocate

CPS(K), LL.B (Hons), LL.M (UoN)

P.O. Box 6496 – 00200, Nairobi

Email: wafulamakokha@gmail.com

Phone: +254 726 419 173

#### Personal Profile

I am a Kenyan Lawyer, and Advocate of the High of Kenya, with experience in human rights advocacy, research, training, litigation and consultancy. I have facilitated national, regional and international human rights trainings and conferences of both communities and professionals including lawyers, judges, health care workers, law enforcement officers, journalists, among others. In addition, I have consulted on health-related human rights, devolution, governance, intellectual property law, employment law, constitutional law and public interest law.

### **EDUCATION**

2018 - 2019: Master of Laws (LLM) (Public International Law)

University of Nairobi, Kenya

Thesis: An Examination of the Legal, Policy and Institutional Framework of

Universal Health Coverage in Kenya

2012 – 2015: Post Graduate Diploma in Law

Kenya School of Law

Bachelor of Laws (LL.B) Degree, 2007 - 2011, University of Nairobi

Certified Public Secretaries (CPS), 2008-2010, Kenya.

### **EXPERIENCE:**

January 2020 to date: Health and Governance Programme Manager

## Kenya Legal and Ethical Issues Network (KELIN), Kenya

- Provide leadership and technical oversight of the health, governance and accountability unit in KELIN Programmes
- Guide the programme team to address the health governance and accountability with a view to ensure service delivery systems are strengthened.
- Liaise with county and sub- county level with finance and health management teams to enhance coordination and collaboration with a view to influence and advocate for good governance and accountability under health care delivery systems.
- Participate as part of the public participation process provided under the law during the national and county budget preparation process.
- Participate as a member of Civil Society in coordination and monitoring county and national government implementation of the approved budgets and financial reporting systems.
- Contribute to the development of health governance and accountability programme strategies, concept notes and donor proposals
- Directly manage KELIN's project that focus on health, governance and accountability both at national and county levels.
- Provide oversight on monitoring both financial audit ensuring recommendations are implemented for fiscal prudence
- Assist in advocacy to inform policy makers and assist in policy review based on program learning and field-based evidence.

- Provide leadership and technical guidance for programming and approaches
- Monitor the programme against objectives outlined in the programme plan and international standards.
- Guide the development of annual work plans in coordination with the project teams.
- Prepare written reports for KELIN and donors (monthly, quarterly and annual) and other reports as required.
- Support field teams on effective and quality programme management and implementation.
- Represent KELIN at County, National and Regional level coordination meetings taskforces and conferences etc related to health governance and accountability
- Represent KELIN at key national technical committees on the development of guidelines, tools, materials for use in health, governance and accountability.
- Maintain good working relationships and co-ordination with County and national partners working in health sector and related sectors and programmes ensuring alignment and harmonization with KELIN objectives and result areas/intervention.

March 2018 – December 2019: Research Officer.

## Parliament of Kenya (Senate)

- Draft bills, order papers, statements and other matters subject of discussion on the floor of the Senate or in committees.
- Review petitions, statements, bills, committee reports and other matters tabled on the floor of the Senate.
- Provide research support to committees and the leadership of the Senate.

- Draft advisory opinions and notes to committees and the leadership of the
  Senate.
- Provide technical support to committees and Senate leadership in conducting their legislative business.

October 2015 – February 2018: Programme Officer

Kenya Legal and Ethical Issues Network (KELIN), Kenya

- Review, analyze and advise on health-related laws, bills, regulations policies, guidelines and operational frameworks at the international, regional, national and county level to identify gaps and ensure they integrate human rights principles;
- Conceptualize and undertake public interest litigation to protect and promote the right to health. This includes client advisory and representation in Courts and Tribunals;
- Train communities and professions (lawyers, law enforcement officers, health care workers etc) on health-related human rights;
- Facilitate international, national and county based dialogues on access to health-related human rights;
- Work with county and national structures to strengthen responsiveness to health rights violations.
- Develop concept notes and proposals for funding of projects.
- Implement projects, and report to donors.

Legal Associate, Gitonga Mwangi & Company Advocates (2014 – 2015)

Research Assistant, Innovative Lawyering (2012 – 2013)

## Professional Membership:

- Member Law Society of Kenya (LSK)
- Member of the Institute of Certified Public Secretaries of Kenya (ICPSK)

### Consultancies undertaken:

- April June 2019: Field Researcher in a baseline assessment on Mixed methods assessment of human rights barriers to HIV, TB and Malaria services and programs to reduce such barriers for key and vulnerable populations in Nairobi, Kisumu and Mombasa, Kenya. The Assessment was conducted by KELIN, JSI and the University of Southern California in the USA for the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria.
- November 2018 January 2019: Developed four *Information Education and Communication materials* on HIV, TB and Human Rights for the project Kenya HIV, TB and Human Rights Training and Advocacy Country Programme (implemented by KELIN, KESWA and Lwala Community Alliance).
- November 2018 January 2019: Developed a policy brief on the social structural and legal barriers and human rights violations that affect realization of the right to health services in relation to HIV, TB and SRHR) for the project Kenya HIV, TB and Human Rights Training and Advocacy Country Programme (implemented by KELIN, KESWA and Lwala Community Alliance).
- Field Researcher in Legal environment assessment of HIV in Kenya
  (October 2018 March 2019) for Health Policy Project.
- Provided Rapporteuring services during the High-Level Meeting on the Nairobi Strategy on Tuberculosis and Human Rights held on 9 – 10
   August, 2018 in Mombasa, Kenya. The High-Level Meeting was

- convened by KELIN, Stop TB Partnership (Switzerland) and Northwestern Pritzker School of Law (USA).
- o Provided rapporteuring services during the *regional capacity building* forum on HIV, TB, human rights and the law for law enforcement officers and health care workers held on 27 29 June 2018 at Sarova Whitesands Hotel, Mombasa, Kenya. The training had participants from 9 African countries and was convened by KELIN (Kenya), SALC (South Africa), ARASA (South Africa), Enda Sante (Senegal) with support from UNDP Regional Office for Africa (Ethiopia).

# Human rights trainings (short courses) undertaken:

- February 2018: I attended a regional training of African Lawyers on "Strategic Litigation, Legal Defence and Advocacy against HIV and TB criminalization" organized by the Southern Africa Litigation Centre (SALC), 20-23 February, Johannesburg South Africa.
- March 2017: I attended a training for African lawyers on "Removing legal barriers to prison health and human rights" organized by the Southern Africa Litigation Centre (SALC) in Johannesburg South Africa (13-15 March 2017).
- February November 2016: I successfully participated in a one-year 4-module Training of Trainers (TOT) Programme on HIV, TB and Human Rights in Southern and East Africa by the AIDS and Rights Alliance for Southern Africa (ARASA), February November 2016.

## Timothy Wafula Makokha

